<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cookie Policy on Massimo Ronca ~ a reckless programmer with a sarcastic wit</title>
    <link>http://massimoronca.it/tags/cookie-policy.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cookie Policy on Massimo Ronca ~ a reckless programmer with a sarcastic wit</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://massimoronca.it/tags/cookie-policy.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>About cookies</title>
      <link>http://massimoronca.it/pages/policy.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://massimoronca.it/pages/policy.html</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;What are cookies in computers?&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Also known as browser cookies or tracking cookies, cookies are small, often encrypted text files, located in browser directories. They are used by web developers to help users navigate their websites efficiently and perform certain functions. Due to their core role of enhancing/enabling usability or site processes,&amp;nbsp;disabling cookies&amp;nbsp;may prevent users from using certain websites.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cookies are created when a user&amp;rsquo;s&amp;nbsp;browser&amp;nbsp;loads a particular website. The website sends information to the browser which then creates a text file. Every time the user goes back to the same website, the browser retrieves and sends this file to the website&amp;rsquo;s server. Computer Cookies are created not just by the website the user is browsing but also by other websites that run ads, widgets, or other elements on the page being loaded. These cookies regulate how the ads appear or how the widgets and other elements function on the page.For Managing cookies for different browsers&amp;nbsp;see here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Standard uses for browser cookies&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Website servers set cookies to help authenticate the user if the user logs in to a secure area of the website. Login information is stored in a cookie so the user can enter and leave the website without having to re-enter the same authentication information over and over.More information&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Session Cookies&amp;nbsp;are also used by the server to store information about user page activities so users can easily pick up where they left off on the server&amp;rsquo;s pages. By default, web pages really don&amp;rsquo;t have any &amp;lsquo;memory&amp;rsquo;. Cookies tell the server what pages to show the user so the user doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to remember or start navigating the site all over again. Cookies act as a sort of “bookmark” within the site. Similarly, cookies can store ordering information needed to make shopping carts work instead of forcing the user to remember all the items the user put in the shopping cart.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Persistent or tracking Cookies&amp;nbsp;are also employed to store user preferences. Many websites allow the user to customize how information is presented through site layouts or themes. These changes make the site easier to navigate and/or lets user leave a part of the user&amp;rsquo;s “personality” at the site. For Information on session and persistent and tracking cookies,&amp;nbsp;see here&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Cookie security and privacy issues&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cookies are NOT viruses. Cookies use a plain text format. They are not compiled pieces of code so they cannot be executed nor are they self-executing. Accordingly, they cannot make copies of themselves and spread to other networks to execute and replicate again. Since they cannot perform these functions, they fall outside the standard virus definition.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cookies CAN be used for malicious purposes though. Since they store information about a user&amp;rsquo;s browsing preferences and history, both on a specific site and browsing among several sites, cookies can be used to act as a form of spyware. Many&amp;nbsp;anti-spyware&amp;nbsp;products are well aware of this problem and routinely flag cookies as candidates for deletion after standard virus and/or spyware scans.See here for some&amp;nbsp;privacy issues and concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The way responsible and ethical web developers deal with privacy issues caused by cookie tracking is by including&amp;nbsp;clear descriptions of how cookies are deployed on their site.&amp;nbsp;If you are a web developer and need advice on implementation of cookies and a privacy policy, we suggest you contact marketing specialists who offer&amp;nbsp;search engine optimisation services. These privacy policies should explain what kind of information is collected and how the information is used. Organizations using the cookies initiative started by IAB Europe include:&amp;nbsp;InviteMedia&amp;nbsp;Networkadvertising.org&amp;nbsp;: andAntor&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most browsers have built in privacy settings that provide differing levels of cookie acceptance, expiration time, and disposal after a user has visited a particular site. Backing up your computer&amp;nbsp;can give you the peace of mind that your files are safe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Other cookie-based threats&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Since identity protection is highly valued and is every internet users right , it pays to be aware of what threat cookies can pose.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;As cookies are transmitted back and forth between a browser and website, if an attacker or unauthorized person gets in between the data transmission, the sensitive cookie information can be intercepted. Although relatively rare, this can happen if the browser is connecting to the server using an unencrypted network like an non-secured WiFi channel.Internet security is only attainable if you regualrly use a anti-virus protection programme.See our&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allaboutcookies.org/security/index.html&#34;&gt;anti virus protection section&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Other cookie-based attacks involve exploiting faulty cookie-setting systems on servers. If a website doesn&amp;rsquo;t require browsers to use encrypted channels only, attackers can use this vulnerability to trick browsers into sending sensitive information over insecure channels. The attackers then siphon off the sensitive data for unauthorized access purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;New Laws for the use of cookies and other technologies that store online user information.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On May 26th 2011, new rules governing the use of cookies by websites comes into force in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Rather than the &amp;ldquo;Opt out&amp;rdquo; option for website visitors, websites will need to specifically gain the consent of their visitor and they must &amp;ldquo;Opt In&amp;rdquo; to be able to store cookies on their computer or other devices.This is expected to be difficult to manage and enforcement will more than likely be done subtlely and with encouragement rather than with the threat of fines and penaltys.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What does the new law say?&lt;br&gt;The new requirement is essentially that cookies can only be placed&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;on machines where the user or subscriber has given their consent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;6 (1) Subject to paragraph (4), a person shall not store or gain&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;access to information stored, in the terminal equipment of a subscriber&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;or user unless the requirements of paragraph (2) are met.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;(2) The requirements are that the subscriber or user of that terminal&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;equipment&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;(a) is provided with clear and comprehensive information about the&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;purposes of the storage of, or access to, that information; and&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;(b) has given his or her consent.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;(3) Where an electronic communications network is used by the&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;same person to store or access information in the terminal equipment&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;of a subscriber or user on more than one occasion, it is sufficient for the purposes of this regulation that the requirements of paragraph (2)&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;are met in respect of the initial use.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;“(3A) For the purposes of paragraph (2), consent may be signified by a&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;subscriber who amends or sets controls on the internet browser which&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;the subscriber uses or by using another application or programme to&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;signify consent.&lt;br&gt;(4) Paragraph (1) shall not apply to the technical storage of, or&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;access to, information&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;(a) for the sole purpose of carrying out the transmission of a&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;communication over an electronic communications network; or&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;(b) where such storage or access is strictly necessary for the&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;provision of an information society service requested by the subscriber&amp;nbsp;&lt;br&gt;or user.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;h3&gt;Key tips for safe and responsible cookie-based Web browsing&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Due to their flexibility and the fact that many of the largest and most-visited websites use cookies by default, cookies are almost unavoidable. Disabling cookies will lock a user out of many of the most widely-used sites on the Internet like Youtube, Gmail, Yahoo mail, and others. Even search settings require cookies for language settings. Here are some tips you can use to ensure worry-free cookie-based browsing:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Customize your&amp;nbsp;browser&amp;rsquo;s cookie settings&amp;nbsp;to reflect your comfort level with cookie security or use the cookie cleaner included in&amp;nbsp;Abine&amp;rsquo;s free Privacy Suite.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are very comfortable with cookies and you are the only person using your computer, you may want to set long expiration time frames for storing your personal access information and browsing history.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you share access on your computer, you may want to set your browser to clear private browsing data every time you close your browser. While not as secure as rejecting cookies outright, this option lets you access cookie-based websites while deleting any sensitive information after your browsing session.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Install and keep antispyware applications updated&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Many spyware detection, cleanup applications, and spyware removers include attack site detection. They block your browser from accessing websites designed to exploit browser vulnerabilities or download malicious software.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make sure your browser is updated&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t already, set your browser to update automatically. This eliminates security vulnerabilities caused by outdated browsers. Many cookie-based exploits are based on exploiting&amp;nbsp;older browsers&amp;rsquo; security shortcomings.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cookies are everywhere and can&amp;rsquo;t really be avoided if you wish to enjoy the biggest and best websites out there. With a clear understanding of how they operate and how they help your browsing experience, you can take the necessary security measures to ensure that you browse the Net confidently.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>